<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ethiopia, Within Easy Reach</title>
    <meta content="01unde" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining, Dining Out/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Dining and Wine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/11/01/dining/reviews/01unde.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1801293"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="$25 AND UNDER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/$25 and Under</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507EFD8123FF932A35752C1A9609C8B63" item-length="678" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ethiopia, Within Easy Reach</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Ethiopia, Within Easy Reach</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter Meehan</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Meehan, Peter</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INJERA'S the thing at Meskel Ethiopian Restaurant. Just about everything is served on a disk of this spongy white bread. Kassech Ayalew, who runs the modestly appointed seven-week-old restaurant in the East Village with her husband, Tefari, will give you a fork and knife if you ask, but it is traditional to tear the bread into small pieces and use it to ferry bites of food to your mouth.</p>
        <p>Injera is about as thick as a diner pancake and as wide as a medium-size pizza. That's where the easy comparisons end: the bread is practically what makes Ethiopian food Ethiopian and appears in few other places in the world.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Meskel Ethiopian Restaurant’s menu proclaims that what it serves is “just home cooking.” It is that, certainly, and so much more.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INJERA'S the thing at Meskel Ethiopian Restaurant. Just about everything is served on a disk of this spongy white bread. Kassech Ayalew, who runs the modestly appointed seven-week-old restaurant in the East Village with her husband, Tefari, will give you a fork and knife if you ask, but it is traditional to tear the bread into small pieces and use it to ferry bites of food to your mouth.</p>
        <p>Injera is about as thick as a diner pancake and as wide as a medium-size pizza. That's where the easy comparisons end: the bread is practically what makes Ethiopian food Ethiopian and appears in few other places in the world.</p>
        <p>It's made from teff, an ancient grain that could be the next big culinary rediscovery but for now is an agrarian oddity outside eastern Africa. At Meskel Mrs. Ayalew makes her injera fresh every day. She mixes ground teff with water to make a batter and lets that batter sit overnight so that it develops a slightly fermented flavor. The next day the breads are quickly cooked on a griddlelike pan.</p>
        <p>What comes out is a vaguely sour flatbread that tastes steamed. Its aroma is stronger than its flavor: anyone who has baked bread at home would associate it with the smell of a loaf of sourdough rye that has risen but is not yet baked.</p>
        <p>Injera works in incredible harmony with the stewed, simmered and sautéed meats, vegetables and legumes that Meskel serves atop it. It adds a necessary sour or acid note to some preparations and, in more than one case, a quiet, bready undertone to a riotously flavorful bite.</p>
        <p>Ethiopian cooking is big on long-cooked onions, fresh ginger, garlic, chilies and clarified butter, so flavor is not in short supply. Mrs. Ayalew manages these ingredients in a way that keeps any one from dominating a dish.</p>
        <p>Take the tibs wat, a dish of braised beef ($12), for example. The first flavor that hits you is butter that has either been infused with spices or has absorbed a good amount of seasoning from the dish as it was cooking. The rich and full flavor of braised beef is next, and it tastes of good quality. (The restaurant also offers it for $12 raw, as gored gored, Ethiopia's answer to steak tartare.) A wash of spice finishes off the tibs wat: chili, yes, but also other spices in such a complex mix and in such fine proportions that trying to identify them is a purely academic exercise.</p>
        <p>Doro wat ($12.95), chicken legs braised with red wine, is equally rewarding. The four braised lamb dishes ($10.95 to $12.45) will work for anyone who likes lamb on the gamy or lamby side.</p>
        <p>But what took me back again and again were the vegetarian dishes at Meskel. The vegetarian combination plate ($12.95) includes a sampling of all of them: red lentils finished with berbere, the same chili and spice combo in the tibs wat; kik alicha wat, a deliciously dusty-tasting preparation of split peas enlivened with ginger and garlic; a heap of cooked collard greens called gomen that I couldn't get enough of; vegetarian meatballs made of ground chickpeas tossed in spicy chili sauce and called shiro wat; sautéed green beans and carrots with ginger, garlic and, though it seems impossible, more. This dish is the best thing to happen to East Village vegetarians in a long time.</p>
        <p>I'm sure the owners of Meskel would blush at such a suggestion. Their menu proclaims that what they serve is ''just home cooking.'' It is that, certainly, and so much more.</p>
        <p>Meskel Ethiopian Restaurant  199 East Third Street (Avenue B), East Village; (212) 254-2411.</p>
        <p>BEST DISHES -- Vegetarian combination platter or any vegetarian dish; doro wat; tibs wat; collard greens.</p>
        <p>PRICE RANGE -- Appetizers, $3 to $6; main courses, $9.75 to $14; side dishes $4.</p>
        <p>CREDIT CARDS -- All major.</p>
        <p>HOURS -- 12:30 to 11:30 p.m. every day.</p>
        <p>WHEELCHAIR ACCESS -- One step up. Restroom too small for wheelchair.</p>
        <p>$25 AND UNDER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
